===BTM字幕组出品===
本字幕仅供交流 切勿商用
神秘博士
50周年特辑
翻译：小吓 零点 小侯爷 小十 叨叨
初校：CC 小侯爷
总校：Miss卷耳
后期：迷毁
==BTM字幕组出品==
"西南风 有阵雨"
"..Wind southwest. Rain at times..."
“与其浪费更多的时间讨论好人的标准
"Waste no more time arguing about what a good man should be.
煤岭中学
岸渠区
校董 I.Chesterton
校长 W.Cobum
不如努力去做个好人”
"Be one."
Marcus Aurelius如是说
Marcus Aurelius.
你是一路跑来的吗
Have you been running?
你还好吗  办公室里有电话找你
Are you OK? There was a call for you, at the office.
是你的医生打来的
From your doctor.
doctor既可指医生 又可指博士 他误把博士当成了Clara的医生
他有没有留下地址?
Did he leave an address?
风大关门
Draught!
书名：高级量子力学
一个星期 先去古代美索不达米亚
Fancy a week in Ancient Mesopotamia...
再到未来火星逛一圈 怎么样
followed by future Mars?
那儿有鸡尾酒吗
Will there be cocktails?
月亮上有
On the moon.
那就去月亮上吧
The moon'll do!
哈哈哈
Ha-ha!
新工作怎么样  教了点什么有意思的吗
How's the new job? Teach anything good?
没有 学了点什么吗
No. Learn anything?
没有
Not a thing.
警报
侦测到TARDIS受干扰
- 发生了什么  - 哇 我们正在起飞
- What's happening?  - Whoa, whoa. We're taking off.
但是发动机没发动啊
But the engines aren't going!
11号直升机呼叫灰狗领队
'Windmill 11 to Greyhound Leader.
蓝鹰正在空运中 准备接收
'Blue Eagle is airborne. Ready to receive.
我们在路上了
'We're on our way.
你好 这是Kate Stewart的手机
Hello, Kate Stewart's phone?
UNIT 伦敦塔
稍等
Oh, hold on.
不好意思 对不起
Excuse me...sorry!
夫人 夫人
Ma'am! Ma'am!
乌鸦看起来都行动迟缓了
The ravens are looking a bit sluggish.
- 跟Malcolm说它们得换新电池了   - 是他
- Tell Malcolm they need new batteries. - It's him!
抱歉 我知道这是您的私人电话 但是 恩
Sorry, it's your personal phone, but, well,
我认出铃声了  是他 对吧
I recognised the ringtone. It's him, isn't it?
快用吸入器
Inhaler.
雾化吸入器 用于治疗上呼吸道疾病 女助理可能患哮喘
博士 你好 我们在郊外找到了TARDIS
Doctor, hello. We found the TARDIS in a field.
- 我正把它运过来   - 你真没开玩笑
- I'm having it brought in. - No kidding!
你在哪
Where are you?
哦 天呐
Oh, my God!
博士 我真抱歉
Oh, Doctor, I'm so sorry,
我们根本不知道你还在里面
we had no idea you were still in there.
快来
Come on.
收到  新目的地 207区  正改变航线
Roger. New heading - 207. Changing course.
啊
Argh...!
- 博士   - Clara
- Doctor?! - Clara!
博士 你能听见我吗
Doctor, can you hear me?
噢
Ow!
- 我想他大概听不到我说话了
- I don't think he can hear me.
- 下次 你们敲一下门会死么
- Next time, would it kill you to knock
我正把你直接送往事发地点
I'm having you taken directly to the scene.
博士 你还好吗
Doctor, hello, are you OK?
我得让你等一会儿了
I'm just going to pop you on hold.
- 博士?   - 啊 博士
- Doctor? - Ah! Doctor!
立正!
Atten...tion!
为什么我要敬礼
Why am I saluting?
博士 作为首席科学官员
Doctor, as Chief Scientific Officer,
请允许我代表UNIT致以正式道歉
may I extend the official apologies of UNIT...?
Kate Lethbridge-Stewart
Kate Lethbridge-Stewart,
聪明人一点即明
a word to the wise.
你父亲肯定跟你讲过
As I'm sure your father would've told you,
我不喜欢被接送
I don't like being picked up.
这话大概在他的脑子听起来更体面些
That probably sounded better in his head.
我正在执行圣谕
I'm acting on instructions direct from the throne.
来自女王伊丽莎白一世的密封指令
Sealed orders from Her Majesty, Queen Elizabeth the First.
女王  一世  等等 伊丽莎白一世
The Queen? The First? Sorry, Elizabeth the First?
她的信任状在里面
Her credentials are inside.
不  是在那里面
No. Inside...
英国国家美术馆 地处伦敦
围巾不错
Nice scarf.
与第4任博士常戴的围巾相似
我们对民众的解释是什么?
What's our cover story for this?
- 额...Derren Brown   - 又是他?
- Um, Derren Brown. - Again?
Derren Brown 英国著名魔术师
我们已经给他寄了花了
Oh, we've sent him flowers.
立正
Atten...tion!
博士之日
注意 美术馆周边要有绝对的安全保障
Right, I want a secure perimeter around the gallery.
你认识她吗  伊丽莎白一世
Did you know her? Elizabeth the First?
- 统一情报工作组   - 什么
- Unified Intelligence Task Force. Sorry?
这群家伙  UNIT
This lot. UNIT.
他们调查外星事物 一切外星的东西
They investigate alien stuff, anything alien.
什么? 比如说你吗?
What, like you?
我为他们工作
I work for them.
你有工作
You have a job?!
我怎么就不能有工作了
Why shouldn't I have a job?
我工作起来可是很酷炫的呢
I'd be brilliant at having a job.
你才没工作呢!
You don't have a job!
我有  这就是我的工作
I do. This is my job,
我现在就在上班啊
I'm doing it now.
你才不会有工作
You never have a job.
我有  我真有
I do! I do.
伊丽莎白的信任状 博士
Elizabeth's credentials, Doctor.
这
But...
这不可能啊
but that's not possible.
不再
No more.
- 这就是标题   - 我知道标题是什么
- That's the title. I know the title!
也被称为Gallifrey陷落
Also known as Gallifrey Falls.
这幅画不属于这里
This painting doesn't belong here -
- 起码不在此时此地   - 当然了
- not in this time or place. - Obviously.
这是阿卡迪亚的陷落
It's the fall of Arcadia,
Arcadia 阿卡迪亚 指世外桃源
那是Gallifrey的第二大城市
Gallifrey's second city.
但是它怎么会这样呢 那怎么可能呢
But how is it doing that? How is that possible?
这是幅油画
It's an oil painting...
还是立体的
..In 3D.
时间领主艺术
Time Lord art.
内部更大  真实时间的一个切片
Bigger on the inside. A slice of real time...
冻结了起来
..Frozen.
伊丽莎白告诉了我们 去哪里能找到它
Elizabeth told us where to find it...
以及它的重要性
and its significance.
你还好吗
You OK?
他曾在那里
He was there.
- 谁在那   - 我
- Who was? - Me.
另一个我
The other me.
我绝口不提的那个
The one I don't talk about.
我不明白
I don't understand.
我有很多张面孔 很多次生命
I've had many faces, many lives.
我并不承认他们所有人
I don't admit to all of them.
有一段生命我很努力地去遗忘
There's one life I've tried very hard to forget.
不再
No more.
他是在时间大战里战斗过的博士
He was the Doctor who fought in the Time War,
而这 正是他做了那件事的日子
and that was the day he did it -
是我做那件事的日子
the day I did it.
那天 他杀死了他们所有人
The day he killed them all.
时间大战的最后一天
The last day of the Time War.
那场止战之战
The war to end all wars
我的种族和Dalek族之间的战争
between my people and the Daleks.
在那场战争里
And in that battle,
有一个人 他手上的鲜血
there was a man with more blood on his hands
比其他所有人都多
than any other.
那人会犯下
A man who would commit
让宇宙都为之寂静的罪孽
a crime that would silence the universe,
而那个人  就是我
and that man...was me.
时间大战的最终之日
消灭
Exterminate!
啊
Argh!
消灭
Exterminate!
给高院的信息 最高次序
Message for the High Council, Priority Omega.
阿卡迪亚已陷落 重复 阿卡迪亚已陷落
Arcadia has fallen. I repeat, Arcadia has fallen.
士兵
Soldier...
我需要你的枪
I'm going to need your gun.
消灭
Exterminate!
求你了 求你了 不要啊
Please! Please, just don't!
警告 警告
Alert! Alert!
探测到博士
The Doctor is detected!
博士已被包围
The Doctor is surrounded!
通知最高指挥官 我们发现了博士
Inform High Command, we have the Doctor!
搜索 定位 毁灭
Seek, locate, destroy!
不再
博士已被包围
The Doctor is surrounded...
搜索 定位 毁灭  搜索
Seek, locate, destroy! Seek...
博士逃跑
The...Doctor...is...escaping.
不再
这些单词是什么
What...are...these...words?
解释
Explain!
高级委员会在开紧急会议
The High Council is in emergency session -
他们有自己的计划了
they have plans of their own.
别管高级委员会了
To hell with the High Council -
Gallifrey-战术室
他们的计划早就失败了
their plans have already failed.
Gallifrey还在水深火热中
Gallifrey's still in the line of fire.
恩 他那时在那里吗
So he was there, then?
他留下了一则消息 给Dalek的书面警告
He left a message, a written warning for the Daleks.
不再
他是个愚人
He's a fool.
不 他是个疯子
No. He's a madman.
你也看到了 长官
As you can see, sir,
包围着整个星球的Dalek舰队
all Dalek fleets surrounding the planet,
如今都集中到了首都
now converging on the capital,
但空中战壕还在顽强支撑
but the Sky Trenches are holding.
Sky Trench 空中战壕：
时间领主用于保护Arcadia的一种防御机制 被认为是不可穿透的
他之后去了哪里
Where did he go next?
这还要紧吗
What does it matter?
这是他们有史以来最猛烈的袭击 长官
This is their biggest ever attack, sir -
- 他们正倾尽全力攻击我们   - 长官
- they're throwing everything at us...   - Sir,
时间地下室出现了安全漏洞
we have a security breach to the Time Vaults.
最终武器库
The Omega Arsenal,
所有禁用武器都紧锁其中
where all the forbidden weapons are locked away.
他们不再是禁用的了
They're not forbidden any more -
我们已经用尽它们来对抗Dalek了
we've used them all against the Daleks.
不
No.
不 我们没有用尽
No, we haven't.
"时刻"不见了
The Moment is gone.
我不明白 "时刻"是什么
I don't understand. What is the Moment?
我从没听说过
I've never heard of it.
星系吞噬者
The galaxy eater.
古Gallifrey人的最后作品
The final work of the ancients of Gallifrey,
这武器极其强大
a weapon so powerful,
以至它的操作系统生出了知觉
the operating system became sentient.
据传说
According to legend...
它发展出了道德心
it developed a conscience.
我们从没用过它吗
And we've never used it?
当一件无限大规模杀伤性武器可以评判你时
How do you use a weapon of ultimate mass destruction
你如何能使用它
when it can stand in judgment on you?
只有一个人会去尝试
There is only one man who would even try.
Gallifrey的时间领主 Skaro的Dalek
Time Lords of Gallifrey, Daleks of Skaro...
我在此通知你们
..I serve notice on you all.
我已太久不问世事 我将不再如此
Too long I have stayed my hand. No more.
今天 你们让我别无选择
Today, you leave me no choice.
今天 这场战争将要结束
Today, this war will end.
不再流血
No more.
不再征战
怎么
How...
你是怎么运作的呢
..How do you work?
为什么从来没有一个红色的大按钮呢
Why is there never a big red button?
有人吗
Hello?
外面有人吗
Is somebody there?
什么都没有
It's nothing.
只是一只狼而已
It's just a wolf.
- 别坐在那个上面   - 为什么不行
- Don't sit on that!   - Why not?
因为这不是一把椅子
Because it's not a chair -
这是全宇宙最危险的武器
it's the most dangerous weapon in the universe.
为什么不能两个都是
Why can't it be both?
为什么你把她停得那么远
Why did you park so far away?
难道你不想让她看见吗
Didn't you want her to see it?
让谁看到
Want who to see?
你的Tar...dis
The TAR...DIS.
你走了好远
You walked for miles.
好长好长好长好长一段路
And miles and miles and miles and miles.
- 我在思考   - 我听见你了
- I was thinking!   - I heard you.
你听见了?
You heard me?
不...再
"No...more."
不再流血
"No more."
'No more.'
- 不再征战   - 不再征战
- "No more."   - No more.
- 不再   - 别说了   - 不再
- "No more!"   - Stop it!   - "No more!"
- 不再   - 你是谁
- "No more."   - Who are you?
它被激活了  快出去
It's activating. Get out of here!
- 嗷   - 怎么了
- Ow!   - What's wrong?
界面好热
The interface is hot.
hot也可指女性热辣性感 此处双关
呵 我可是尽力了
Well, I do my best.
里面有一个能量源
There's a power source inside...
你就是界面
You're the Interface?
他们一定告诉过你"时刻"是有道德心的
They must have told you the Moment had a conscience.
你好呀
Hello!
哦 瞧瞧你
Oh, look at you.
在一个小姑娘和一个盒子间进退两难
Stuck between a girl and a box.
这就是你的人生故事 是吧 博士
Story of your life, eh, Doctor?
你认识我
You know me?
我听见了你
I hear you.
所有版本的你
All of you,
都在你那尘封老旧的脑子里喋喋不休
jangling around in that dusty old head of yours.
这张脸和这个形态是我特地为你选的
I chose this face and form especially for you.
她来自你的过去
It's from your past.
也有可能是你的未来  我总把这两个搞混
Or possibly your future. I always get those two mixed up.
我没有未来
I don't have a future.
我想我叫
I think I'm called...
Rose Tyler
Rose Tyler.
不 对 不 抱歉
No, yes, no, sorry.
不 不 在这个形态下 我叫
No, no, in this form, I'm called...
恶狼
..Bad Wolf.
见新版S01E13
你害怕大恶狼吗 博士
Are you afraid of the big bad wolf, Doctor?
别叫我博士
Stop calling me Doctor.
那是你脑中浮现的名字
That's the name in your head.
不该是这样的
It shouldn't be.
我已经身处这场战争很久了
I've been fighting this war for a very long time -
我不再有权力成为博士
I've lost the right to be the Doctor.
那你就是我们的救世主
Then you're the one to save us all.
是啊
Yes.
如果我发展出了自负心理
If I ever develop an ego,
就会采用你的形象了
you've got the job.
如果你曾在我脑中
If you have been inside my head...
那你一定知道我都目睹过什么
..Then you know what I've seen.
那些苦难
The suffering.
时间与空间中的每个时刻都在燃烧
Every moment in time and space is burning.
这必须停止
It must end.
我打算用我唯一可行的办法来结束这场战争
And I intend to end it the only way I can.
你要用我来结束这场战争
And you're going to use me
用我杀死他们所有人
to end it by killing them all,
所有的Dalek和时间领主一同被毁灭
Daleks and Time Lords alike.
我可以 但你会承担相应的后果
I could, but there will be consequences for you.
我并无苟且偷生之念
I have no desire to survive this.
那么 那就是对你的惩罚
Then that's your punishment.
如果你这么做 如果你
If you do this - if you
杀了他们所有的人 - 那后果就是
kill them all - then that's the consequence.
你  会活下去
You...live.
Gallifrey
Gallifrey...
你会亲手焚毁她
you're going to burn it...
所有的Dalek会与之共焚
and all those Daleks with it
但那些孩子也一样
but all those children too.
现在Gallifrey上有多少个孩子
How many children on Gallifrey right now?
我不知道
I don't know.
有一天你会细数的
One day you will count them.
在某个可怕的夜晚
One terrible night.
你想知道那会把你变成什么样的人吗
Do you want to see what that will turn you into?
拜托  你难道不好奇吗
Come on! Aren't you curious?
我开了一扇通向你未来的窗口
I'm opening windows on your future.
通往未来之日的时间结
A tangle in time through the days to come,
通向今时今日所成就的那个你
to the man today will make of you.
好吧 我可没料到这个
OK, I wasn't expecting that.
但时间大战已经结束了
But the Time War's over.
为什么你把我们带到这儿来看这幅画
Why have you brought us here to look at a painting?
这幅画仅仅是伊丽莎白的信任状
The painting only serves as Elizabeth's credentials,
用来证明那封信是她的亲笔
proof that the letter is from her.
这不是你们来这儿的原因
It's not why you're here.
我最爱的你
My dearest love,
我希望这幅名为"Gallifrey陷落"的油画
I hope the painting known as Gallifrey Falls
能向你证明
will serve as proof that
现在在写信给你的是你的伊丽莎白
it is your Elizabeth who writes to you now.
你该记得
You will recall that you pledged yourself
你发过誓要保卫我的王国
to the safety of my kingdom.
于是 我以女王之名任命你为
In this capacity, I have appointed you as curator
地下美术馆的馆长
of the Under Gallery where
那里锁着全英国最致命的隐患
deadly danger to England is locked away.
那几堵墙内若有任何风吹草动
Should any disturbance occur within its walls,
召你至此就是我最大的心愿
it is my wish that you be summoned.
一路平安 我温柔的夫君
God speed, gentle husband.'
发生了什么
What happened?
直接带你去看吧
Easier to show you.
我是McGillop
McGillop.
但那不可能 我刚还在...
But that's not possible. I was just...
明白 长官 但...
Understood, sir. But...
为什么我要把它带去那里
why would I take it there?
伊丽莎白一世  你认识她咯
Elizabeth the First? You knew her, then?
很久以前的事了
A long time ago.
英格兰 1562年
我们走
Allons-y!
这下你相信了吧 女王陛下 我跟你说了什么
There you go, Your Majesty, what did I tell you?
里面比外面大
Bigger on the inside!
门可不够大  你险些把我的头给削下来
The door isn't - you nearly took my head off.
一般来说我才是干这事的人
It's normally me who does that.
告诉我 博士 为什么我要
Tell me, Doctor, why I'm
在你身上浪费时间 我还要策划战争呢
wasting my time on you. I have wars to plan.
因为你要跟我野餐啊
You have a picnic to eat.
你可以来帮我
You could help me.
呃
Well...
我在帮你吃野餐
I'm helping you eat the picnic.
但是你对战争也有好胃口
But you have a stomach for war.
这张脸目睹过战斗
This face has seen conflict -
一目了然
it's clear as day.
哦 我目睹过你无法置信的战争
Oh, I've seen conflict like you wouldn't believe.
但不是这张脸
But it wasn't this face.
但别纠结那个了 女王陛下
But never mind that, Your Majesty -
站起来  起来  起来
up on your feet! Up, up!
你大胆包天
How dare you?!
我可是英国女王
I'm the Queen of England!
我可不是英国人
I'm not English.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth,
你愿意嫁给我吗
will you marry me?
哦 天呐 亲爱的  我当然愿意
Oh, my dear, sweet love. Of course I will!
- 啊  被我识破啦   - 亲爱的
- Ah! Gotcha!   - My love?
首先  真正的伊丽莎白
One! The real Elizabeth
绝不会答应我的求婚
would never have accepted my marriage proposal.
其次 真正的伊丽莎白会注意到
Two! The real Elizabeth would notice
我刚才随口提到了我有另外一张脸
when I just casually mention having a different face.
不过 真正的伊丽莎白
But then the real Elizabeth
也不是一个外太空来的变形外星人
isn't an alien shape-shifting from outer space!
而且
And...
叮
..Ding.
那是什么
What's that?
那是一个会..."叮"的机器
It's a machine that goes...ding!
我自己做的
Made it myself.
它探测到变形者的DNA就会闪一下  噢
It lights up in the presence of shape-shifter DNA. Ooh.
而且它可以微波加热20英尺之内的冷冻晚餐
Also it can microwave frozen dinners from up to 20 feet
也可以从未来下载漫画书
and download comics from the future.
我总不懂得何时停下
I never know when to stop.
亲爱的 我不明白
My love, I do not understand.
我不是你的亲爱的  而且 你心里明白得很
I'm not your love. And yes, you do!
你是一个Zygon
You're a Zygon.
一个Zygon
A Zygon?
哦 得了吧 别装了  一个Zygon 是的
Oh, stop it, it's over! A Zygon, yes.
一个巨大的红色橡胶怪 全身长满吸盘
A big red rubbery thing, covered in suckers.
但吻技出人意料得高超
Surprisingly good kisser.
想想也不可能 真正的英国女王会
Think the real Queen of England would just decide
决定跟一个长相帅气
to share the throne with
穿着紧身西装的家伙分享王权
any old handsome bloke in a tight suit...
就只是因为他有帅气惊人的发型
Just cos he's got amazing hair
和一匹好马吗
and a nice horse?
噢
Oh.
是那匹马
It was the horse!
我要当国王了
I'm going to be King!
跑   - 发生了什么
Run!   - What's happening?
我们在被
We're being attacked
一个外太空的变形外星人袭击
by a shape-shifting alien from outer space,
它之前还变成了我的马
formerly disguised as my horse.
那是什么意思
What does that mean?
就是说... 我们需要一匹新马了
It means... we're going to need a new horse.
它要去哪里
Where's it going?
我去拖住它 你快跑  你的人民需要你
I'll hold it off, you run. Your people need you.
我要你活着跟我步入婚姻殿堂
And I need you alive for our wedding day.
哦 干得好 博士 真不错
Oh, good work, Doctor, nice one!
童贞女王吗  历史有点吃不消啊
The Virgin Queen? So much for history!
加把力
Come on!
我知道你在那里
Know you're there!
哇 哇 哇 哇
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa...
哦 很聪明
Oh, very clever.
无论你在策划什么 放弃吧
Whatever you've got planned, forget it.
我是博士
I'm the Doctor.
我已经904岁了
I'm 904 years old.
我来自于Kasterborous星系
I'm from the planet
的Gallifrey星
Gallifrey in the constellation of Kasterborous.
我是预至的风暴 我是黑暗的使者
I am the Oncoming Storm, the bringer of darkness,
而你 基本上就只是只兔子 是吧
and you are basically just a rabbit, aren't you?
好吧 继续  只是  一个 常规的
OK, carry on - just a...general...
警告
warning.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth!
那个东西  你跟我解释清楚
That thing...explain what it is!
它想从我们这得到什么
What does it want of us?
那也是我想弄明白的 可能只是你的星球吧
That's what I'm trying to find out. Probably just your planet.
离开她 博士 那不是我 那是那个东西
Step away from her, Doctor. That's not me, that's the creature.
那怎么可能 她是我
How is that possible? She's me.
博士 她竟然是我
Doctor, she's me!
我 的确 是我
I am, indeed, me.
你可永远得不到这句赞扬呢
A compliment that cannot be extended to yourself.
太神奇了
Extraordinary!
那个东西竟然和我一模一样
The creature has captured my exact likeness -
这太了不起了
this is exceptional.
了不起?  一位女王会说这是犯上无礼
Exceptional? A Queen would call it impertinent.
一位女王会情不自禁地想要
A Queen would feel compelled to admire
欣赏处决的技术
the skill of the execution -
之后她就要下令了
before arranging one.
啊  它坏掉了
Ah! It's not working!
可以推断这怪物会很快学会
One might surmise the creature would learn quickly
保护自己 不会被简简单单地探测出来
to protect itself from any simple means of detection.
很明显你比我更了解这怪物
Clearly you understand the creature better than I.
不过你本就有优势
But then you have the advantage.
退后 你们俩都退后 快
Back, both of you, now!
那是时间裂隙 现实结构中的裂口
That's a time fissure, a tear in the fabric of reality.
什么都有可能发生
Anything could happen!
比如
For instance...
一顶土耳其毡帽
a fez.
这边走
This way.
欢迎来到地下美术馆
Welcome to the Under Gallery.
伊丽莎白一世在这里存放所有
This is where Elizabeth the First kept all art
太危险而不适于向公众展示的艺术品
deemed too dangerous for public consumption.
岩粉
Stone dust.
那重要吗
Is it important?
1200年来 我从未踩在不重要的东西上面
In 1,200 years, I've never stepped in anything that wasn't.
喂 你  你搞科学么
Oi, you! Are you sciencey?
噢 呃  那个 是的
Oh, erm. Well, erm...yes.
- 你有名字吗   - 是的
Got a name? Yes.
太好了 我一直想碰见个名叫"是的"的人
Good, I've always wanted to meet someone called Yes.
好 分析这些岩粉
Now, I want this stone dust analysed.
给我一式三份的报告
And I want a report in triplicate,
里面要有好多图表 示意图和复杂的数字计算
with lots of graphs and diagrams and complicated sums,
明天一早 送到我桌上 尽快 立刻 哈哈哈
on my desk, tomorrow morning, ASAP, pronto, LOL.
看到没  我有工作
See? Job.
我有办公桌吗
Do I have a desk?
- 没有   - 我还想要张桌子
- No.   - And I want a desk!
去组织一个小组 分析这些岩粉
Get a team, analyse the stone dust.
快用吸入器
Inhaler!
总有一天 你能对土耳其毡帽视而不见吧
Someday, you could just walk past a fez.
永远不可能
Never going to happen.
按您的指示 没有碰任何东西
As you instructed, nothing has been touched.
这是我们叫你来的原因
This is why we called you in.
又是3D的
3D again.
- 有意思   - 你说碎掉的玻璃吗
- Interesting.   - The broken glass?
不
No...
是玻璃打碎的方向
where it's broken from.
看看它破碎的图案
Look at the shatter pattern.
所有画上的玻璃
The glass on all these paintings
都是从里面打破的
has been broken from the inside.
如你所见 所有的画都是风景
As you can see, all the paintings are landscapes -
- 没有任何人物   - 那又如何
- no figures of any kind. - So?
曾经有的
There used to be.
有东西从画里出来了吗
Something's got out of the paintings?
很多东西
Lots of somethings.
危险的东西
Dangerous.
这整个地方都被搜查过了
This whole place has been searched.
没有发现不属于这儿的异物
There's nothing here that shouldn't be,
也没有东西从这儿出去
and nothing's got out.
哦 不  别是现在
Oh, no! Not now!
博士 那是什么
Doctor, what is it?
别是现在 我忙着呢
No, not now. I'm busy!
它和画有关吗
Is it to do with the paintings?
不 不 这是别的  我记得这个
No, no. This is different. I remember this.
差不多记得
Almost remember...
噢 当然了
Oh, of course!
是轮到我上场的时候了
This is where I come in.
走咯
Geronimo-o...
博士  等等
Doctor! Wait.
这个男人是谁
Who is this man?
我也在想这个问题
That's just what I was wondering.
噢 那真瘦
Oh, that is skinny.
真是骨感啊
That is proper skinny.
我从来没从外面看过
I've never seen it from the outside.
像特效一样  喂  哈  瘦火柴棍
It's like a special effect. Oi! Ha! Matchstick man!
你不是
You're not...
为了补偿吧   - 补偿什么
Compensating? - For what?
重生效果 碰运气的事儿
Regeneration, it's a lottery.
噢 他很酷 不是吗
Oh, he's cool. Isn't he cool?
"我是博士 我很酷
"I'm the Doctor and I'm all cool -
哎呀呀 我穿着沙滩鞋呢"
oops, I'm wearing sandshoes!"
你在这干什么 我忙着呢
What are you doing here? I'm busy.
噢 忙吗  我知道了 这就叫忙着 对吗
Oh, busy? I see, is that what we're calling it, eh? Eh?
你们好啊 女士们   - 少来
Hello, ladies. - Don't start.
你在这一任重生
Listen, what you get up to
的私人时间里干了些什么不关我的事儿
in the privacy of your own regeneration is your business.
他们里有一个Zygon
One of them is a Zygon.
恶
Urgh...
我可没在评判你
I'm not judging you.
哦 太可爱了
Oh, lovely!
陛下们... 或许你们该跑了
Your Majesties...probably a good time to run.
- 但那怪物怎么办   - 伊丽莎白
- But what about the creature? - Elizabeth, whichever one of you
不论你们中哪个是真的
is the real one, turn and
向另一个跑的反方向跑
run in the opposite direction to the other one.
好的 吾爱
Of course, my love!
要活着 吾爱
Stay alive, my love.
我们还没有结束
I am not done with you yet.
谢谢 很好
Thanks. Lovely.
我理解 为我活下去 亲爱的
I understand. Live for me, my darling.
我们会重聚的
We shall be together again.
那个 这样也挺好吧?
Well, won't that be nice?
- 其中一个是Zygon   - 没错
- One of those was a Zygon. - Yeah.
巨大的红色橡胶怪
Big red rubbery thing.
- 满身吸盘   - 没错
- Covered in suckers.   - Yeah.
舌头上有毒囊
Venom sacs in the tongue.
- 没错 我懂了 谢谢提醒   - 很好
- Yeah, I'm getting the point, thanks. - Nice.
博士 是你吗
Doctor? Is that you?
啊 你好 Clara  你能听到吗
Ah! Hello, Clara! Can you hear me?
是我 我们能听见 你在哪
Yeah, it's me, we can hear you. Where are you?
- 我们在哪   - 英国 1562年
- Where are we? - England...1562.
你在和谁说话
Who are you talking to?
我自己
Myself.
你能回来吗
Can you come back through?
实体通道不一定是双向的
Physical passage may not be possible in both directions.
是... 对了
It's... Ah!
等等 毡帽来了
Hang on! Fez incoming!
什么都没有
Nothing here.
那它去哪了
So where did it go?
- 他在和谁说话   - 他刚说了 他自己
- Who's he talking to?  - He said. Himself.
继续和他说话  Malcolm吗
Keep him talking. Malcolm?
我需要你给我拿
Malcolm, I need you to send me
我父亲的一份事件档案  代码是Cromer
one of my father's incident files - codenamed Cromer.
70或80年代的 取决于记年方式
'70s or '80s, depending on the dating protocol.
好了 你曾经是我
OK, you used to be me,
你都做过这些了 接下来会怎样
you've done all this before - what happens next?
我不记得了
I don't remember.
你怎么能忘了这个
How can you forget this?!
等等 又不是我的错
Hey, hang on, it's not MY fault.
很明显是你
You're obviously not
注意力不集中 快把极性倒转
paying enough attention. Reverse the polarity!
- 没用啊   - 我们都在倒转极性
- It's not working. - We're both reversing the polarity!
是啊 我知道
Yes, I know that.
有两个人 我在倒转极性
There's two of us - I'm reversing it,
你又把它倒转回来 我们让极性混乱了
and you're reversing it back again! We're confusing the polarity.
有谁把毡帽弄丢了吗
Anyone lose a fez?
是你
You.
你怎么会在这
How can you be here?
更重要的是 你为什么来这
More to the point, WHY are you here?
下午好
Good afternoon.
我...在找博士
I'm...looking for the Doctor.
这个嘛 你还真来对地方了
Well...you've certainly come to the right place.
很好  不错
Good! Right!
你们是什么人
Well, who are you boys?
噢 当然了  你们是他的同伴吗
Oh, of course! Are you his companions?
他的同伴
His companions?
博士的同伴越来越年轻了
They get younger all the time!
那个 你能不能给我
Well, if you could point
大致指一下博士在哪
me in the general direction of the Doctor...
真的吗
Really?
是的
Yeah.
- 是真的   - 你们是我? 两个都是?
- Really.   - You're me? Both of you?
- 是的   - 那个也是?
Yep. Even that one?
对
Yes!
你们是我将来的自己
You're my future selves.
对
Yes!
我中年危机了吗
Am I having a mid-life crisis?
你们干嘛那样拿螺丝起子指着
Why are you pointing your screwdrivers like that?
那是科学仪器 又不是水枪
They're scientific instruments, not water pistols.
你们活像见鬼了似的
Look like you've seen a ghost!
不过 我挺喜欢这幅行头
Still...loving the posh,
又时髦又沧桑  很让人信服
gravelly thing. It's very convincing.
说得好 Dick Van Dyke
Brave words, Dick Van Dyke.
Dick Van Dyke 著名演员 作品有等
包围他们
Encircle them!
你们谁是博士
Which of you is the Doctor?
英格兰女王被施了魔咒
The Queen of England is bewitched.
我要拿下博士的项上人头
I would have the Doctor's head.
你今天真是走运啦
Well, this has all the makings of your lucky day.
我觉得现在有三个博士了
I think there's three of them now.
这事有过先例
There's a precedent for that.
那是什么
What is that?
哦 又开始指指戳戳了 那是螺丝起子
Oh, the pointing again. They're screwdrivers!
你们能干什么 用他们组装个柜子吗
What are you going to do, assemble a cabinet at them
那玩意  那是什么巫术
That thing...what witchcraft is it?
啊 没错
Ah, yes!
既然你提到了 这就是巫术 对对对
Now that you mention it, that is witchcraft, yes, yes, yes.
很坏很坏的巫术  喂
Witchy-witchcraft. Hello?
有人吗  有人吗 喂
Hello in there? Excuse me. Hello!
我是在与井中的邪恶女巫对话吗
Am I talking to the wicked witch of the well?
他指的是你
He means you.
为什么我是女巫
Why am I the witch?
- Clara   - 你好
- Clara? - Hello?
Clara 嗨 你好
Clara, hi, hello.
你能不能让这些啰嗦的凡人
Hello. Would you mind telling these prattling mortals
自觉走开呢
to get themselves begone?
如  如他所言
What...he said.
好吧 再润色润色嘛
Yes, tiny bit more colour.
好吧
Right.
啰嗦的凡人 尔等走开
Prattling mortals, off you pop,
不然我把你们都变成青蛙
or I'll turn you all into frogs.
哦 青蛙呀 不错 你们都听到了
Oh, frogs, nice. You heard her.
博士 发生什么了
Doctor, what's going on?
这是 时间乱乱了
It's a...timey-wimey thing.
时间 怎么了  时间乱乱
Timey...what? Timey-wimey?
我可不知道他从哪学会的这句话
I've no idea where he picks that stuff up.
女王
The Queen!
你们似乎没有下跪呀
You don't seem to be kneeling.
多么大胆
How tremendously brave of you.
你是哪一个
Which one are you?
- 另一个怎么了   - 偶感不适
- What happened to the other one?   - Indisposed.
- 女王万岁   - 女王万岁
- Long live the Queen! - Long live the Queen!
逮捕他们 押送至塔楼
Arrest these men. Take them to the Tower.
那不是英格兰女王  那是个外星复制品
That is not the Queen of England - that's an alien duplicate!
你们得相信他
And you can take it from him,
- 他真的检查过了   - 哦 闭嘴吧
- cos he's really checked.   - Oh, shut up!
- 舌头上有毒囊   - 拜托你 闭嘴吧
- Venom sacs in the tongue.   - Seriously, stop it!
不 等等 塔楼 你说塔楼吗
No, hang on, the Tower! Did you say the Tower?
啊 绝妙 爱死那座塔了 请八点送早饭
Ah, yes, brilliant, love the Tower. Breakfast at eight, please.
那有Wi-Fi吗
Will there Wi-Fi?
你说话时能不手舞足蹈吗
Are you capable of speaking without flapping your hands about?
可以  看来不行
Yes! No!
我要求立刻被监禁在塔中
I demand to be incarcerated in the Tower immediately
与我的合谋者一起
with my co-conspirators,
- 沙滩鞋小子和老爷爷   - 老爷爷
- Sandshoes and Grandad! - Grandad?
- 这不是沙滩鞋   - 这就是
- They're not sandshoes. - Yes, they are!
安静  塔楼不容轻视
Silence! The tower is not to be taken lightly.
很少有人重见天日
Very few emerge again.
天啊 那人好聪明 来吧
Dear God, that man's clever. Come on!
我们去哪
Where are we going?
我的办公室  大家也叫它伦敦塔
My office. Otherwise known as the Tower of London.
喂 你们几个 滚进去
Oi, you lot, get in there!
啊
Ow!
我们三人在一个囚室里
Three of us in one cell -
如果不赶紧出去
that's going to cause some
肯定会引发一些严重的异象
nasty anomalies if we don't get out soon.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
- 把我们弄出去   - 音速起子
- Getting us out! - The sonic
对那门没用 太原始了
won't work on that - it's too primitive.
我们应该要求提高牢门质量让我们好逃跑吗
Shall we ask for a better quality of door so we can escape?
好吧 现在英格兰女王是个Zygon
OK, so the Queen of England is now a Zygon,
不过别管那个 我们为什么聚在了一起
but never mind that, why are we all together?
我们为什么都在这
Why are we all here?
我和...下巴君 我们都很意外
Well, me and...Chinny, we were surprised.
但你是来找我们
But you came looking for us -
你知道这会发生  谁告诉你的
you knew it was going to happen. Who told you?
喂 "下巴君"什么意思
Oi! "Chinny"?
没错 你下巴的确出众
Yeah, you do have a chin.
大理石 花岗岩... 许多不同的岩石
Marble, granite... A lot of different stone,
但都不是来自那座建筑体的
but none of it from the fabric of the building.
就好像有人砸碎了许多古老的雕塑
It's like somebody smashed up a lot of old statues.
有失踪的雕像吗
Are there any missing?
我觉得没有
Don't think so.
怎么会有人那么做
Why would anyone do that anyway?
我是说 我知道我们应该思想开放
I mean, I know we're meant to keep an open mind,
但我们真要相信
but are we supposed to believe in creatures
有生物能藏在油画里
that can hide in oil paintings
并对雕塑心怀怨恨吗
and have some sort of a grudge against statues?
你还好吗
You all right?
我们必须离开 现在 此刻
We have to go - right now, this minute.
怎么了
What's wrong?
那些油画里的东西
The things from the paintings...
我知道他们为什么要砸碎雕像了
I know why they smashed the statues.
- 为什么   - 因为他们需要藏身之地
- Why? - Because they needed somewhere to hide.
博士会来救我的 博士会来救我的
The Doctor will save me, the Doctor will save me,
the Doctor will save me, the Doctor will save me,
博士会来救我的 博士会来救我的
the Doctor will save me, the Doctor will save me...
抱歉  我需要我的吸入器
Excuse me - I'm going to need my inhaler.
我复制了一个有缺陷的 真讨厌
I so hate it when I get one with a defect!
噢 你心里可有一些绝佳的可怕回忆
Oh, you've got some perfectly horrible memories in here,
不是么
haven't you?
那么嫉妒你那个可爱的妹妹
So jealous of your pretty sister.
我不怪你 我也希望我复制的是她
I don't blame you, I wish I'd copied HER.
我也希望
So do I!
噢 看在上帝的份儿上
Oh, for goodness' sake...!
博士会试着给我们留消息
The Doctor will be trying to send us a message.
我们要寻找一串大约留于
We're looking for a string of numerals
1550年的字符  最高优先级
from around 1550, approximately - priority one.
我需要进入黑色档案馆
I'm going to need access to the Black Archive.
黑色档案馆
The Black Archive.
地球上安全等级最高的地方
Highest security rating on the planet.
全体员工在一次轮班结束时
The entire staff have their
都会被抹去记忆
memories wiped at the end of every shift.
自动记忆过滤器就装在天花板上
Automated memory filters in the ceiling.
- 请让我进入   - 是 夫人
- Access, please.  - Ma'am.
你是Atkins 对吗
Atkins, isn't it?
是的 夫人  第一天当班
Yes, ma'am. First day here.
他已经工作十年了
Been here ten years
锁与钥匙  有点原始 不是么
Lock and key - bit basic, isn't it?
我们可不敢把电子安保系统装在这里
Can't afford electronic security down here -
得防着博士进来
got to keep the Doctor out.
整座塔都是防Tardis入侵的
The whole of the Tower is TARDIS-proofed.
他可不会喜欢这里的藏品
He really wouldn't approve of the collection.
可你让我进来了
But you let me in?
你的上一次访问给了你最高安全等级
You have a top-level security rating from your last visit.
抱歉 我的啥
Sorry, my what?
抱歉  我们必须筛查所有已知的博士联系人
Apologies. We have to screen all of his known associates -
我们不能让博士与TARDIS
we can't have information about the Doctor and the TARDIS
被不恰当的人掌控
falling into the wrong hands.
会有灾难性的后果
The consequences could be disastrous.
那是什么
What is that?
时间旅行
Time travel.
漩涡操纵器  Jack Harkness上校
A vortex manipulator, bequeathed to the UNIT archive
去世时捐赠给UNIT的
by Captain Jack Harkness, on the occasion of his death.
他的某一次去世时
Well, one of them.
不能让任何人知道我们有这个
No-one can know we have this,
- 甚至我们的同盟也不行   - 为什么
- not even our allies.  - Why not?
想想吧
Think about it!
拥有改写历史能力的美国人
Americans with the ability to rewrite history?
你也看过他们的电影了
You've seen their movies.
好吧 所以我们就要这么去营救博士
OK, so this is how we're going to rescue the Doctor.
我不确定它的能量是否足够往返
I'm not sure there's enough power for a two-way trip.
无论如何 我们不知道激活码
In any event, we don't know the activation code.
博士知道我们有这东西
The Doctor knows we have this,
所以他总不把激活码告诉我们
so he's always kept the code from us.
但愿他改变主意了
Let's hope he changes his mind.
是我
Yes.
如果你找到了
Well, if you've found it,
就赶紧拍下来 发到我手机上
photograph it and send it to my phone.
呃 Kate  他们该在这儿吗
Erm, Kate. Should they be here?
他们为什么跟着我们
Why have they followed us?
噢 他们大概只是
Oh, they've probably just
太早处理完人类了
finished disposing of the humans a bit early.
人类?
The humans...?
天啊  我太入戏了不是吗
Dear me! I really do get into character, don't I?
地下美术馆已经被我们掌握
The Under Gallery is secured.
准备再处理一个人类吧
Prepare to dispose of one more human.
我们已经取得了设备
We have acquired the device.
激活码  对吧
Activation code - right?
理论上来说 我可以
In theory, I can
触发分子间的独立声波位移
trigger an isolated sonic shift
这门也就分崩离析了
among the molecules, and the door should disintegrate.
我们得计算出整个结构的具体共振频率
We'd have to calculate the exact harmonic resonance
要精确到亚原子级别
of the entire structure down to a sub-atomic level.
就算用音速起子也需要好多年
Even the sonic would take years.
不 不  用音速起子需要好几个世纪
No, no. The sonic would take centuries.
噢 我们最好现在就开始
Oh, we might as well get started.
能打发"时间乱乱"
Help to pass the "Timey-wimey".
你一定要像个小孩儿一样说话吗
Do you have to talk like children?
你为什么耻于长大成熟呢
What is it that makes you so ashamed of being a grown-up?
噢 你们俩看我的眼神
Oh, the way you both look at me.
那是什么意思啊
What is that?
我想找一个比"可怕"更好的词来形容
I'm trying to think of a better word than "Dread".
那件事对你来说一定刚发生不久
It must be really recent for you.
不久
Recent?
时间大战 最终之日
The Time War, the last day.
你杀死他们所有人的那一日
The day you killed them all.
我们杀死他们所有人的那一日
The day WE killed them all.
一回事
Same thing.
这对他们是历史  已经尘埃落定了
It's history for them. All decided.
他们觉得他们的未来是真实的  他们不了解
They think their future is real - they don't know
这仍然取决于你
it's still up to you.
我不会谈论它的
I don't talk about it.
你没有谈论它
You're not talking about it.
这儿没有别的人
There's no-one else here.
继续啊 问问他们
Go on. Ask them.
问问他们你需要知道的
Ask them what you need to know.
你们有没有数过
Did you ever count?
数过什么
Count what?
那天 Gallifrey星上有多少孩子
How many children there were on Gallifrey that day.
我完全不知道
I have absolutely no idea.
你现在多大了
How old are you now?
啊… 我不知道 我记不清了
Ah...I don't know, I lose track.
我想有1200多岁吧 除非我在撒谎
Twelve hundred and something, I think, unless I'm lying.
我记不得我有没有在年龄上撒谎了
I can't remember if I'm lying about my age -
我就有那么老了
that's how old I am.
比我大400岁
400 years older than me.
在这期间
And in all that time,
你就从没有想过那儿有多少个孩子吗
you've never even wondered how many there were?
你就一次也没有数过
You never once counted?
你告诉我
Tell me...
那有什么意义呢?
what would be the point?
2.47亿
2.47 billion.
你真的算过了
You DID count!
你忘了
You forgot?
才400年  就把这些都泯灭了
400 years? Is that all it takes?
我向前看了
I moved on.
到哪了  你现在前进到了哪儿
Where?! Where can you be
足以让你忘记这样的事
now that you can forget something like that?
- 天机不可泄露   - 不是
- Spoilers.  - No.
不 不是 不是的  就这一次
No, no, no. For once,
我想要知道自己将会去向何方
I would like to know where I'm going.
不  你不会想知道的
No. You really wouldn't.
我不知道你们俩是谁  我一个都不认识
I don't know who you are... either of you.
我一点都不清楚
I haven't got the faintest idea.
他们就是你
They're you.
他们就是你的未来
They're what you become
如果你毁灭了Gallifrey
if you destroy Gallifrey.
一个悔恨之人
The man who regrets...
还有一个健忘之人
..And the man who forgets.
那一时刻就要来了
The moment is coming.
那时刻就是我 你必须做出决定
The Moment is me, you have to decide.
不
No.
No?
就只是 不
Just...no!
有什么好笑的吗  我错过了哪个笑点吗
Is something funny? Did I miss a funny thing?
抱歉  我就是刚刚想到
Sorry. It just occurred to me.
我一个人的时候就是这样
This is what I'm like when I'm alone.
那是同一个音速起子
It's the same screwdriver.
同样的软件  不同的外壳
Same software...different case.
400年
400 years!
怎么了
I'm sorry?
就软件层面来说
At a software level,
他们是同一个东西 不是吗
they're all the same device, aren't they?
同样的软件 不同的外壳
Same software, different case.
是啊  所以…
Yeah. So...?
所以  音速起子要用几个世纪来计算
So, it would take centuries for the screwdriver to calculate
如何瓦解这扇门  扫描门
how to disintegrate the door. Scanning the door,
把这个运算作为一个永续进行的子程序
implanting the calculation as a permanent subroutine
植入软件系统里
in the software architecture
那么  如果你们真的是我
and...if you really are me,
穿着你那沙滩鞋 戴着你那蝴蝶领结
with your sandshoes and your dicky bow,
而那起子仍然是我的
and that screwdriver is still mine...
那个运算就还在进行
..That calculation is still going on.
是啊  还在运行
Yeah. Still going.
运算完成
Calculation complete.
同样的软件  不同的外壳
Same software. Different face.
哎  400年压缩成了4秒钟
Eh, 400 years in four seconds.
我们也许意见不合
We may have our differences,
在这种情况里还真是奇怪
which is frankly odd in the circumstances,
但是我告诉你们 伙计们
but I tell you what, boys,
我们真是聪明绝顶啊
we are incredibly clever!
你怎么做到的
How did you do that?
- 这门没锁   - 好吧
- It wasn't locked.  - Right.
他们都是你 是吧
So they're both you, then, yeah?
是的  你之前见过他们 还记得吗
Yes. You've met them before, don't you remember?
记得一点  很棒的套装啊
A bit. Nice suit!
谢了
Thanks.
等一下
Hang on.
三个你挤在一个牢房里
Three of you in one cell,
就没一个能想到来试试这扇门吗
and none of you thought to try the door.
它应该是锁上的啊
It should have been locked.
是啊 就是  为什么它没上锁
Yes, exactly! Why wasn't it locked?
因为我很想看看
Because I was fascinated to see
你们会怎么逃跑
what you would do upon escaping.
我知道你们都很爱这个世界
I understand you're rather fond of this world.
可我想是时候让你们看看将要发生什么了
It's time I think you saw what's going to happen to it.
啊
Ah!
Kate  噢 上帝 你没真的死掉
Kate? Oh, goodness, you're not actually dead.
噢 这可真是重大新闻
Oh, that's tremendous news!
那些生物 他们会把自己变成人们的复制品
Those creatures, they turn themselves into copies.
他们需要让原型活着 刷新影像
And they need to keep the original alive, refresh the image,
可以这么说吧
so to speak.
他们  他们去哪儿了
Where...where did they go?
我不知道  噢 等等
I don't know. Ooh, hang on -
对了我知道  他们去塔里了
yes, I do. The Tower.
如果他们成功进入了黑色档案馆
If those creatures have got access to the Black Archive,
我们可能已经失去控制这颗星球的力量了
we may just have lost control of the planet.
Zygons一族失去了他们自己的世界
The Zygons lost their own world.
时间大战一开始就被焚毁了
It burned in the first days of the Time War.
他们需要一个新家
A new home is required.
所以他们想要这一个
So they want this one?
还不到时候  这里过于原始了
Not yet. Far too primitive.
Zygons对于舒适性有一定要求
Zygons are used to a certain level of comfort.
指挥官
Commander...
为什么这些生物会在这儿
..Why are these creatures here?
因为我让他们在这儿
Because I say they should be.
你也是时候该转译了
It is time you too were translated.
好好看着吧
Observe this.
我相信你们会觉得非常有趣的
I believe you will find it fascinating.
那个是他  就是现在画里的那个Zygon
That's him! That's the Zygon in the picture now.
那不是画  那是一个静态立方
It's not a picture, it's a Stasis Cube.
时间领主艺术
Time Lord art -
冻结的瞬间时刻 里面比外面大
frozen instants in time, bigger on the inside
但是可以用来
but could be deployed as...
- 进入暂停模式  - 噢 这可真棒
- Suspended animation. - Oh, that's very good.
所有的Zygons都被保存在了图片里
The Zygons all pop inside the pictures,
等上个几世纪
wait a few centuries
直到这颗星球变得更有趣一点
till the planet's a bit more interesting,
然后他们再出来
and then out they come.
你瞧 Clara
You see, Clara,
他们被储存在
they're stored in the
地下美术馆的画中 就像是罐装汤饮
paintings in the Under Gallery, like Cup-a-Soups.
除了你加入罐子里的是时间
Except you add time -
如果你能想象出来的话
if you can picture that.
没人能想象出那个  忘了我说的罐装汤饮吧
Nobody could picture that. Forget I said Cup-a-Soups.
现在 这个世界已经变得值得侵占了
And now the world is worth conquering.
Zygons便由过去
So the Zygons are invading the future
入侵未来
from the past.
正是这样
Exactly!
然后你知道我怎么看出你是赝品的吗
And do you know why I know that you're a fake?
因为你是份极差的复制品
Because you're such a bad copy.
不仅是味道 或是假冒伪劣的头发
It's not just the smell, or the unconvincing hair,
还是你那穷凶极恶的牙
or the atrocious teeth,
还有靠得有点太近的两眼
or the eyes just a bit too close together,
或者可以熏晕一匹马的口气
or the breath that could stun a horse -
是因为我的伊丽莎白 真正的伊丽莎白
it's because my Elizabeth, the real Elizabeth,
从来不会蠢到透露她自己的计划
would never be stupid enough to reveal her own plan.
说实在的 你为什么要那么做
Honestly, why would you do that?
因为这不是我的计划
Because it's not my plan,
而且 我就是真的伊丽莎白
and I AM the real Elizabeth.
好吧  能不能 倒回一点
OK. So...backtracking a moment,
给我刚刚的话加点背景信息
just to lend some context to my earlier remarks...
我的复制品死在了树林里
My twin is dead in the forest.
我习惯采取预防措施
I am accustomed to taking precautions.
这些Zygon生物甚至想都没想过
These Zygon creatures never
我会是幸存下来的那个
even considered that it was me
而不是他们的指挥官
who survived, rather than their own commander.
他们的特点就是骄傲自大
The arrogance that typifies their kind.
Zygon么?
Zygons?
男人们!
Men!
你真的杀了他们中的一个吗
And you actually killed one of them?
我也许只是个手无缚鸡之力的女子
I may have the body of a weak and feeble woman,
但那时 那个Zygon也一样
but at the time, so did the Zygon.
我王国的未来处于危险之中
The future of my kingdom is imperilled.
博士 我能依靠你吗
Doctor, can I rely on your service?
嗯 我得需要我的Tardis
Well, I'm going to need my TARDIS.
- 已经准备好了   - 啊哈
- It has been procured already.  - Ah!
但是首先 我亲爱的 你有个承诺要遵守
But first, my love, you have a promise to keep!
我现在宣布 你们正式结为夫妇
I now pronounce you...man and wife.
你可以亲吻新娘了
You may kiss the bride.
这种事儿在未来有很多吗
Is there a lot of this in the future?
是啊 它确实开始发生了
It does start to happen, yeah.
一路平安 我的爱人
God speed, my love.
我马上就回来
I will be right back.
喔
Whoo!
好吧 回到未来
Right, then, back to the future.
你让这地方自生自灭了啊
You've let this place go a bit!
啊 那是他的丑陋时代 他会长大的
Ah, it's his grunge phase. He grows out of it.
别听他们胡说
Don't you listen to them!
噢  控制台出问题了
Ooh! The desktop is glitching.
我们三个来自不同时间
Three of us from different time zones,
它正在试着抵消
it's trying to compensate.
嘿 看 那些圆圆的东西
Hey, look, the round things.
我超爱那些圆圆的东西
I love the round things.
那些圆的到底是什么
What ARE the round things?
不知道
No idea.
哦 天呐 冲突反销器
Oh, dear, the friction contrafibulator.
哈  看 稳定了
Ha! There! Stabilized.
哦 你重新装修过了
Oh, you've redecorated!
我不喜欢
I don't like it.
噢  噢 对 噢
Oh? Oh, yeah. Oh,
你永远都不喜欢  听着 我们要去
you never do! Listen, we're going
国家美术馆  Zygon们在地下
to the National Gallery - the Zygons are underneath it.
不 是UNIT总部
No, UNIT HQ,
他们跟着我们去了黑色档案馆
they followed us there in the Black Archive.
好吧  你们现在都知道了
OK...so you've heard of that, then.
UNIT 伦敦塔
这里的设备都非同寻常
The equipment here is phenomenal.
人类都不知道这里一大半的设备
The humans don't realise
是用来做什么的
what half this stuff does -
凭借它们 我们一天之内就能征服他们的世界
we could conquer their world in a day.
那我们很幸运
We were fortunate, then...
选择了正确的复制对象
in our choice of duplicate.
如果我是人类 我会称之为圣诞狂欢
If I were human, I'd say it was Christmas.
不 恐怕你们的美梦要落空了
No. I'm afraid you wouldn't.
我们没有武器  你们不必紧张
We're not armed. You may relax.
我们有武器  你们需要紧张
We are armed. You may not.
锁住大门
Lock the door.
恐怕我们不能被打断
I'm afraid we can't be interrupted.
不介意我舒舒服服地坐下吧
You don't mind if I get comfortable?
不介意我也这么做吧
You don't mind if I do?
你们知道存在保护此地的协议吧
You'll realise there are protocols protecting this place.
- Osgood   - 如遇外星人入侵
- Osgood...   - In the event of alien incursion,
这间房间内的物体被判定极为危险
the contents of this room are deemed so dangerous,
它会自我毁灭 就在... 在五分钟后
it will self-destruct in... Five minutes.
在我们下方20英尺 有一个核弹头
There's a nuclear warhead 20 feet beneath us.
你坐得还舒服么
Are you sitting comfortably?
你会摧毁伦敦吗
You would destroy London?
为了拯救这个世界  是的 我会的
To save the world? Yes, I would.
你只是在虚张声势
You're bluffing.
你真的那么认为吗
You really think so?
在你的记忆中 有一个男人
Somewhere in your memory is a man called
他叫Brigadier Alistair Gordon Lethbridge-Stewart
Brigadier Alistair Gordon Lethbridge-Stewart.
我是他的女儿
I'm his daughter.
"科学至上" Kate
"Science leads," Kate.
你那句话就想表达这个吗
Is that what you meant?
这就是你父亲想表达的么?
Is this what your father meant?'
- 博士   - 时空电报 Kate
- Doctor?   - Space-Time Telegraph, Kate.
时空电报
这是我给你父亲的礼物
A gift from me to your father,
直通TARDIS的专线
hotline straight to the TARDIS.
我知道黑色档案馆
I know about the Black
我也知道安全协议
Archive and I know about the security protocol.
Kate 求你
Kate, please,
请你告诉我
please, tell me you are not
你不会做出什么蠢得惊人的事
about to do something unbelievably stupid!
我很抱歉 博士  把它关掉
I'm sorry, Doctor. Switch it off.
你晚些会更抱歉的
Not as sorry as you will be.
你永远都承受不了这个决定的后果
This is not a decision you will ever be able to live with.
Kate 我们正试着把TARDIS开过去
Kate! We're trying to bring the TARDIS in -
为什么我们无法降落
why can't we land?
我说把它关掉
I said switch it off!
不要 Kate 求你 听我说
No, Kate, please, just listen to me...
伦敦塔 完全防TARDIS
The Tower of London - totally TARDIS-proof.
他们怎么做到的
How can they do that?
外星科技加上人类的愚蠢
Alien technology plus human stupidity -
相信我 那就战无不胜了
trust me, it's unbeatable.
我们不需要降落
We don't need to land.
我们多少还是要的  争取跟上吧
Yeah, we do, a tiny bit. Try and keep up.
不一定  不一定  还有别的方法
No, we don't. We don't. There is another way.
罐装汤饮
Cup-a-Soup!
罐装汤饮是什么
What is Cup-a-Soup?
出什么事了
What happened?
直接带你去看吧
Easier to show you.
我是McGillop
McGillop.
看一眼电话 确认你在和谁说话
Take a look at your phone and confirm who you're talking to.
但那不可能啊 我刚刚
But that's not possible. I was just...
你刚刚还在和我说话 我知道
You were just talking to me, I know.
我是个时间旅行者 想得明白吧
I'm a time traveller - figure it out.
我需要你把
I need you to send the
Gallifrey陷落的油画送到黑色档案馆去
Gallifrey Falls painting to the Black Archive.
- 明白吗   - 明白 长官
- Understood? - Understood, sir.
但为什么要把它送到那里去
But why would I take it there?
你说句话就可以取消倒计时
One word from you would cancel the countdown.
没错
Quite so.
你的声纹就是钥匙
It's keyed to your voice print.
只有我一个人的
And mine alone.
不再是了  取消爆炸
Not any more. Cancel the detonation!
- 指令撤回   - 取消爆炸
- Countermanded! - Cancel the detonation!
指令撤回
Countermanded!
我们得求同才能生存
We only have to agree, to live.
很不幸 我们只能一同死亡了
Sadly, we can only agree to die.
求你 博士  请救救我们
Please, Doctor. Please save us.
请救救我们 请救救我们
Please save us. Please save us.
救救我们
Please save us...
消灭
Exterminate!
大家好
Hello.
我是博士
I'm the Doctor.
抱歉有个Dalek
Sorry about the Dalek.
还有卖弄
Also the showing off.
Kate Lethbridge-Stewart
Kate Lethbridge-Stewart,
以明智的名义 你究竟在干什么
what in the name of sanity are you doing?
倒计时只能在我的个人指令下停止
The countdown can only be halted at my personal command.
你无能为力
There's nothing you can do.
除了让你们两个都同意中止
Except make you both agree to halt it.
即使有三个你也做不到
Not even for three of you.
你将杀害百万人
You're about to murder millions of people.
以此拯救数十亿人
To save billions.
你做过多少次这种计算了
How many times have you made that calculation?
只有一次
Once.
将我变成了现在的样子
Turned me into the man I am now.
我都不确定我是谁了
I'm not even sure who that is any more.
你告诉自己你有正当理由 但那是个谎言
You tell yourself it's justified, but it's a lie.
因为我那天的所作所为是错误的  完全错了
Because what I did that day was wrong. Just wrong.
因为我做错了
And because I got it wrong...
我会让你... 做正确的事
I'm going to make you... get it right.
怎样
How?
从现在起的某一秒 你们要停止倒计时
Any second now, you're going to stop that countdown.
你们两个 一起
Both of you. Together.
然后你们要
Then you're going to
谈妥有史以来最完美的协定
negotiate the most perfect treaty of all time.
防护员就在近旁 对双方都很公正
Safeguards all around, compeletly fair on both sides.
完美谈判的关键就在于
And the key to perfect negotiation...
不知道你站在哪一边
Not knowing what side you're on.
所以 接下来的几个小时
So, for the next few hours...
直到我们决定放你们出去为止
until we decide to let you out...
在这间房间里的人都
No-one in this room will
不会记得他是人类
be able to remember if they're human...
还是Zygon
..Or Zygon.
好呀
Whoops-a-daisy!
取消爆炸
Cancel the detonation!
和平降临我们的时代了
Peace in our time.
很有趣 不是吗
It's funny, isn't it?
如果我是Zygon 那我的衣服也是Zygon
If I'm a Zygon, then my clothes must be Zygon too.
如果我丢掉一只鞋会怎样呢
So, what happens if I lose a shoe or something?
哎呀
Oh!
你好
Hello.
- 你好   - 我是Clara
Hello. I'm Clara.
我们还没真正见过面呢
We haven't really met yet.
我很期待认识你
I look forward to it.
有问题吗
Is there a problem?
博士 我是说我的
The Doctor - my...
我的博士
my Doctor -
他总是谈论他做出那件事的那天
he's always talking about the day he did it,
他毁灭所有时间领主来终止战争的那一天
the day he wiped out the Time Lords to stop the war...
他有理由谈论它
One would.
而你不会
You wouldn't.
因为你还没有做
Because you haven't done it yet.
那还在你的未来里
It's still in your future.
你对此非常自信
You're very sure of yourself.
他很后悔 我每天都能从他眼睛里看出来
He regrets it. I see it in his eyes every day.
他会不惜一切改变当时发生的事
He'd do anything to change it.
包括拯救这些人么
Including saving all these people.
你觉得 他的悔恨拯救了多少个世界呢
How many worlds has his regret saved, do you think?
看看那边吧
Look over there -
人类和Zygon和平地解决问题
humans and Zygons working together in peace.
你怎么知道我还没做
How did you know?
你的眼睛
Your eyes.
你年轻许多
You're so much younger.
那么 综合考虑
Then, all things considered...
是我成长的时候了
..It's time I grew up.
我已经眼见了我需要看的一切
I've seen all I needed.
时刻到了
The moment has come.
我准备好了
I'm ready.
我知道
I know you are.
谁在那  你在和谁说话
Who's there? Who were you talking to...?
你想要个红色的大按钮的
You wanted a big red button.
一场大爆炸 不再有时间领主
One big bang - no more Time Lords,
不再有Dalek
no more Daleks.
你确定吗
Are you sure?
我进来前就确定了
I was sure when I came in here.
没有别的出路
There is no other way.
你看到了你将要变成的人
You've seen the men you will become.
他们
Those men...
非同寻常
extraordinary.
他们就是你
They were you.
不
No.
他们是博士
They were the Doctor.
你也是
You're the Doctor too.
不
No.
烈火铸就伟人
Great men are forged in fire.
小人有幸点燃烈火
It is the privilege of lesser men to light the flame...
无论代价几何
..Whatever the cost.
你知道TADRIS的声音吗
You know the sound the TARDIS makes?
那呼哧呼哧的呻吟声
That wheezing...groaning.
那声音无论到往何处 都能带来希望
That sound brings hope wherever it goes.
是的 是的 我喜欢这么想
Yes. Yes, I like to think it does.
给每一个听到的人 博士
To anyone who hears it, Doctor.
任何人 不管他怎样迷失
Anyone, however lost...
即使是你
..Even you!
我告诉过你 他还没有做
I told you - he hasn't done it yet.
离开这 你们全都离开
Go away now, all of you.
这事由我来做
This is for me.
这些事件都应该被时间锁定了
These events should be time locked -
我们甚至都不该在这儿
we shouldn't even be here.
是有什么东西让我们通过了
So something let us through.
机灵的男孩们
You clever boys!
回去
Go back.
回到你们的生活
Go back to your lives.
去做那个我永远不能成为的博士
Go and be the Doctor that I could never be.
让这一切都值得
Make it worthwhile.
这么多年 我将你埋藏于记忆中
All those years, burying you in my memory.
假装你并不存在
Pretending you didn't exist.
将你当作秘密 甚至对我自己
Keeping you a secret, even from myself.
假装你不是博士
Pretending you weren't the Doctor,
你却比任何人都够格做博士
when you were the Doctor more than anybody else.
你就是博士
You were the Doctor on
在不可能做出正确选择的日子
the day it wasn't possible to get it right.
但这次
But this time...
你不必一人完成
..You don't have to do it alone.
谢谢
Thank you.
我们今日的作为 不是出于恐惧或者仇恨
What we do today is not out of fear or hatred.
我们如此作为 是因为别无选择
It is done because there is no other way.
是以我们没能拯救的无数生命之名
And it is done in the name
来完成这件事
of the many lives we are failing to save.
什么
What?
是什么 怎么了
What is it, what?
没事
Nothing...
不对 有事  告诉我
No.It's something. Tell me!
你告诉我 你毁灭了自己的种族
You told me you wiped out your own people.
我只是...
I just...
我从来没有想象过你这么做 就这样
I never pictured you doing it, that's all.
近一些看
Take a closer look.
这是什么
What's happening?
什么都没有 这只是投影
Nothing - it's a projection.
这是你们身边的现实
It's a reality around you.
你们要焚毁这些人吗
These are the people you're going to burn?
我们无能为力
There isn't anything we can do.
他说得对
He's right.
没有另一条出路 从来就没有
There isn't another way, there never was.
我要么毁灭我的同胞 要么任由宇宙焚毁
Either I destroy my own people or let the universe burn.
看看你们
Look at you...
你们三个
..The three of you.
一个战士 一个英雄
The warrior. The hero.
还有你
And you.
我是什么
And what am I?
你真的忘记了吗
Have you really forgotten?
是的 也许 是的
Yes. Maybe, yes.
我们有足够的战士
We've got enough warriors -
随便一个老傻瓜也能当英雄
any old idiot can be hero.
那我要做什么
Then what do I do?
做你一直在做的
What you've always done.
当个博士(医生)
Be a doctor!
你说过你选择的名字是个承诺
You told me the name you chose was a promise.
是什么承诺呢
What was the promise?
永不残酷也不懦弱
Never cruel or cowardly.
永不放弃
Never give up,
永不屈服
never give in.
你不是真的在建议
You're not actually suggesting
我们改变自己的历史吧
that we change our own personal history?
我们一直都在改变历史
We change history all the time.
我只是在提议糟糕得多的事
I'm suggesting something far worse.
究竟 是什么
What, exactly?
先生们 我用了400年的时间来思考这件事
Gentleman, I have had 400 years to think about this.
我改主意了
I've changed my mind.
那里仍有成百上千亿亿的Daleks在攻击
There's still a billion billion Daleks up there, attacking.
是的 一直都有
Yeah, there is, there is.
可是有一些事
But there's something
是那么多的Daleks都不知道啊
those billion billion Daleks don't know.
因为如果他们知道的话
Cos if they did,
他们很可能会加派援军了
they'd probably send for reinforcements.
它们还不知道什么?
What, what don't they know?
这次 我们有三个呢
This time, there's three of us.
噢
Oh!
哦  哦 是的 太棒了
Oh! Oh, yes, that is good!
真是好主意
That is brilliant!
噢 噢 噢  我也想到了  真是聪明绝顶
Oh, oh, oh! I'm getting that too - that is brilliant!
哈哈哈  我都想了几世纪了
Ha-ha-ha! I've been thinking about it for centuries!
她不是随便找了段未来给我看
She didn't just show me any old future -
她给我看了我正需要看到的未来
she showed me exactly the future I needed to see!
- 现在你正跟上了   - 什么 谁做的
- Now you're getting it.  - Eh? Who did?
噢 恶狼姑娘 我都要亲你了!
Oh, Bad Wolf Girl, I could kiss you.
是的 以后那会发生的
Yep, that's going to happen.
打扰下 你刚说了什么 恶狼
Sorry, did you say, "Bad Wolf"?
那我们要做什么  计划是什么
So what are we doing? What's the plan?
Daleks部队正围攻Gallifrey
The Dalek fleets are surrounding Gallifrey,
进行持续不断的炮火攻击
firing on it constantly.
空中战壕还在支撑
The Sky Trench is holding,
可要是整个星球消失了会怎样呢
but what if the whole planet just disappeared?
我再问一小点点
Tiny bit of an ask.
Daleks就会相互射击
The Daleks would be firing on each other -
他们会在交叉火力中自我毁灭
they'd destroy themselves in their own crossfire.
Gallifrey会消失 Daleks被毁灭
Gallifrey would be gone, the Daleks would be destroyed,
在宇宙的其他部分看来
and it would look to the rest of the universe
就像他们相互毁灭了一样
as if they'd annihilated each other.
- 但Gallifrey会在哪   - 冻结起来
- But where would Gallifrey be?  - Frozen!
冻结在一瞬的时间中
Frozen in an instant of time,
安全地隐藏起来
safe and hidden away.
没错
Exactly!
就像一幅油画
Like a painting.
又一条消息
Another one!
Gallifrey
伫立不倒
你确定消息来自于他
Are you sure the message is from him?
是的  可他为什么要这么做呢
Oh, yes! Why would he do that?
这个疯疯癫癫的傻子现在又说什么了
What's the mad fool talking about now?
你好 你好 Gallifrey最高指挥部
Hello, hello, Gallifrey High Command,
我是博士
this is the Doctor speaking.
你好  我也是博士 你能听得我讲话吗
Hello! Also the Doctor. Can you hear me?
我也是博士 准备好了
Also the Doctor - standing ready.
上帝啊 有三个博士
Dear God, three of them!
我所有最可怕的噩梦同时再现了
All my worst nightmares at once!
统帅 我们有个计划
General, we have a plan.
我们得指出 此时此刻
We should point out, at this moment,
这是个很糟糕的计划
it is a fairly terrible plan.
而且几乎肯定会失败
And almost certainly won't work.
说"很糟糕"已经足够了吧
I was happy with "Fairly terrible".
抱歉 我刚把心里想法说出来了
'Sorry, just thinking out loud.'
我们正把我们的三个TARDIS飞到你们的低空
We're flying our three TARDISes into your lower atmosphere.
我们在星球周围等距布阵
We're positioned at equidistant intervals round the globe.
等距  听起来真成熟
"Equidistant" - so grown-up!
我们准备好要做了
We're just about ready to do it.
准备好做什么?
Ready to do what?
我们将要封存Gallifrey
We're going to freeze Gallifrey.
不好意思 你说什么
I'm sorry, what?
利用我们的TARDIS
Using our TARDISes,
我们要把Gallifrey封存在时光里的一瞬
we're going to freeze Gallifrey in a single moment in time.
你知道的 就像静态立方一样
You know, like those Stasis Cubes?
时光中的一瞬 封存在平行的口袋宇宙中
A single moment in time held in a parallel pocket universe.
不过 我们将对整个星球这么做
Except we're going to do it to a whole planet.
以及星球上的所有人
And all the people on it.
什么 即使这是可能的
What? Even if that were possible,
而实际上不可能 你们为什么要这么做?
which it isn't,why would you do such a thing?
因为另一个选择是焚毁星球
Because the alternative is burning.
我亲眼目睹过
And I've seen that.
我永远都不想再看一次了
And I never want to see it again.
我们会在另一个宇宙迷失的
We'd be lost in another universe...
封存于一瞬间中
..Frozen in a single moment.
我们就一无所有了
We'd have nothing.
你们还会有希望
You would have hope.
但现在 你们却连希望也没有
And right now, that is exactly what you don't have.
真是妄想 光是运算
It's delusional. The calculations alone
就会花上几百年的时间
would take...hundreds of years.
是的 数以百年的时间
Oh, hundreds and hundreds.
不过别担心
But don't worry -
很早之前我就开始算了!
I started a very long time ago!
呼叫Gallifrey军事委员会
Calling the War Council of Gallifrey,
我是博士
this is the Doctor.
你可以说 我的一生都在做这个
You might say, I've been doing this all my lives!
- 好运   - 准备好了
- Good luck!  - Stand by.
- 好了吗   - 开始计算
- Ready?  - Commencing calculations.
马上就到
Soon be there.
穿越分割宇宙的界限
Across the boundaries that divide one universe from another.
只要锁定它的坐标就行
Just got to lock on to his coordinates.
还有我的下个把戏
And for my next trick...!
我真不知道什么时候能过得好点
I didn't know when I was well off!
一共12个博士
All 12 of them!
不 先生
No, sir...
是13个
..All 13!
长官  Dalek发现不对劲了
Sir! The Daleks know that something is happening.
他们在增加火力
They're increasing their fire power.
做吧 博士
Do it, Doctor.
尽管做吧
Just do it.
这么做吧
Do it!
好
Ok.
先生们 我们准备好了
Gentleman...we're ready.
我们来了
Geronimo...!
走咯
Allons-y!
噢 看在上帝的份上
Oh, for God's sake!
Gallifrey伫立不倒
Gallifrey stands!
我想我们永远也不会知道我们有没有真的成功
I don't suppose we'll ever know if we actually succeeded.
但就算再糟
But at worst,
我们也只是没做成功正确的事
we failed doing the right thing,
而不是做成功了错误的事
as opposed to succeeding in doing the wrong.
说起生命和灵魂 你可真深奥
Life and soul, you are.
这究竟叫什么
What is it actually called?
恩 有些争议
Well, there's some debate.
要么是 不再
Either No More
要么是 Gallifrey陷落
or Gallifrey Falls.
这可不够鼓舞人心
Not very encouraging.
它怎么到这的
How did it get here?
不清楚
No idea.
总有些我们不知道的事 对吧
There's always something we don't know, isn't there?
是该这么希望
One should certainly hope so.
那 先生们
Well, gentlemen...
和你们共事是我的荣耀
it has been an honour...
和荣幸
and a privilege.
我也是 博士
Likewise. Doctor.
要是我能成为你的一半
And if I grow to be half the man
那么好的人 Clara Oswald
that you are, Clara Oswald,
我会很欣慰的
I shall be happy indeed.
那就对了  要胸怀大志哦
That's right - aim high!
我不会记得这个的 对吧
I won't remember this, will I?
时间流不同步了
The time streams are out of sync.
你不会保留这个记忆 不
You can't retain it, no.
所以我不会记得我曾奋力援救Gallifrey
So I won't remember that I tried to save Gallifrey,
而不是烧毁它
rather than burn it.
我不得不接受并勉力活下去
I'll have to live with that.
但是现在
But for now,
此刻
for this moment...
我又成为了博士
..I am the Doctor again.
谢谢你们
Thank you.
哪个是我的
Which one is mine?!
哈
Ha!
噢 是的
Oh, yes...
当然 这就对了
Course, suppose it makes sense...
我都有点等得不耐烦了
Wearing a bit thin.
吐槽九叔的招风耳
我希望这次耳朵能不那么显眼
I hope the ears are bit less conspicuous this time.
我也不会记得这个 所以你还是告诉我吧
I won't remember either, so you might as well tell me.
告诉你什么
Tell you what?
你一直不想说的 我们将去向何方
Where it is we're going that you don't want to talk about.
我看到了Trenzalore
I saw Trenzalore...
我们将被埋葬在那里
where we're buried.
我们和百万人一同死于战场
We die in battle among millions.
不应如此
That's not how it's supposed to be.
故事就是这么结束的  我们无力改变
That's how the story ends - nothing we can do about it.
Trenzalore就是你最终去处
Trenzalore is where you're going.
噢 话别说绝了
Oh, never say nothing.
不论如何
Anyway...
很高兴知道我的未来是安全的
good to know my future is in safe hands.
要看紧些啊 Clara
Keep a tight hold on it, Clara.
恩  没问题
Mm! On it!
Trenzalore
Trenzalore.
我们需要个新的目的地 因为
We need a new destination, because...
我不想去
..I don't want to go.
"I don't want to go."
10任重生前的最后一句话 "我不想走"
他总是那么说
He always says that.
你需要和你的画独处一会儿吗
Need a moment alone with your painting?
你怎么知道的
How did you know?
- 那双悲伤的大眼睛   - 啊
- Those big, sad eyes. - Ah.
我总是知道的
I always know.
哦 对了 有个老人找你
Oh, by the way, there was an old man looking for you.
我觉得他是馆长
I think it was the curator.
我也可以做馆长
I could be a curator.
我会干得很好的
I'd be great at curating.
我会是一个... 很棒的馆长
I'd be...the great curator.
我可以退休然后干这行
I could retire and do that.
我可以退休以后在这里做馆长
I could retire and be the curator of this place.
其实 我真觉得你有可能会这么做
You know, I really think you might.
我从不会忘记一张脸
I never forget a face.
我知道你不会 而且在将来
I know you don't, and in years to come,
第四任博士的演员 Tom Baker
你也许会发现自己重新换上了几个老面孔
you might find yourself revisiting a few
不过只是... 那些最喜欢的老面孔 是吧
but just...the old favourites, eh?
我猜 你对这幅画很好奇
You were curious about this painting, I think.
我在十分不寻常的情形下得到了它
I acquired it in remarkable circumstances.
你觉得它的标题怎么样
What do you make of the title?
哪个标题  有两个呢
Which title? There's two.
不再
No More...
或是Gallifrey陷落
..Or Gallifrey Falls?
哦 你瞧 人人都把这搞错
Oh, you see, that's where everybody's wrong.
只有一个名字
It's all one title.
Gallifrey不再陷落
Gallifrey Falls No More.
现在 你觉得那是什么意思 恩
Now, what would you think that means, eh?
Gallifrey没有陷落
That Gallifrey didn't fall.
成功了  它还存在着
It worked. It's still out there.
我只是个小小的馆长  我可什么都不知道
I'm only a humble curator - I'm sure I wouldn't know.
- 那它在哪   - 是啊 它在哪
- Then where is it? - Where is it indeed?
失落了 别说了 也许吧
Lost. shh! perhaps.
东西都是会丢的 你知道
Things do get lost, you know.
现在 失陪了
Now you must excuse me.
噢
Oh...
你有好多事情要做
you have a lot to do.
是吗   - 嗯
Do I? - Mm.
我现在该做这事了吗
Is that what I'm supposed to do now?
去寻找Gallifrey?
Go looking for Gallifrey?
噢 那完全取决于你  是你的选择
Oh, it's entirely up to you. Your choice.
我只能告诉你我会怎么做
I can only tell you what I would do,
如果我是你的话
if I were you...
噢 如果我是你
Oh...! If I were you...
也许我曾是你 当然
Perhaps I WAS you, of course.
不过也许...
Or perhaps...
你是我
you are me.
祝贺你
Congratulations.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
或者怎样都不重要
Or perhaps it doesn't matter either way.
谁知道呢
Who knows?
谁... 又知道呢
Who...knows?
此处以手指鼻子(nose) 与知道(knows)谐音
Clara有时问我 我会不会做梦
Clara sometimes asks me if I dream.
"我当然会做梦" 我告诉她
"Course I dream," I tell her.
"人人都会做梦"
"Everybody dreams."
"但你会梦到什么呢" 她会问
"But what do you dream about?" She'll ask.
"人人都会梦到的东西" 我告诉她
"The same thing everybody dreams about," I tell her.
"我梦到我去的地方"
"I dream about where I'm going."
她总会笑起来
She always laughs at that.
"但你哪也不去呀
"But you're not going anywhere -
你只是乱逛而已"
you're just wandering about."
那不对  不再是
That's not true. Not any more.
我有了一个新的目的地
I have a new destination.
我的旅程和你们的一样 和所有人都一样
My journey is the same as yours, the same as anyone's.
它花费了我那么多年 那么多次生命
It's taken me so many years, so many lifetimes,
但我终于知道我将去往何处
but at last I know where I'm going,
我一直在去往何处
where I've always been going.
回家  只不过绕了漫漫长路
Home...the long way round.'